We are at a remarkable moment in time.
نحن نمر بلحظة زمنية هامة.
We face over the next two decades
سنواجه خلال العقدين القادمين
two fundamental transformations
تحوّلين أساسيّين
that will determine whether the next 100 years
يحددان إن كانت المائة عام القادمة
is the best of centuries or the worst of centuries.
هي أفضل القرون أم أسوأها.
Let me illustrate with an example.
فلأعطكم مثالا.
I first visited Beijing 25 years ago
زرت بكين أوّل مرة منذ 25 سنة
to teach at the People's University of China.
لأدرّس بجامعة الصّين الشعبيّة.
China was getting serious about market economics
الصّين بدأت تركّز على اقتصاد الأسواق
and about university education,
وعلى التّعليم العالي،
so they decided to call in the foreign experts.
فقرّروا مناداة خبراء أجانب.
Like most other people,
كغالبيّة النّاس،
I moved around Beijing by bicycle.
كنت أتنقّل بالدّرّاجة.
Apart from dodging the occasional vehicle,
بالإضافة إلى تفادي السّيّارة المستعملة،
it was a safe and easy way to get around.
فقد كانت طريقة آمنة وسهلة للتّنقّل.
Cycling in Beijing now
التّنقّل بدرّاجة الآن في بكين
is a completely different prospect.
أمر مختلف تماما.
The roads are jammed by cars and trucks.
الطّرقات مكتظّة بالسّيّارات والشّاحنات.
The air is dangerously polluted
الهواء متلوّث بصفة خطيرة
from the burning of coal and diesel.
نتيجة احتراق الفحم والدّيزل.
When I was there last in the spring,
حين كنت هناك في الرّبيع الماضي،
there was an advisory for people of my age —
نصح النّاس من عمري
over 65 —
- أي 65 فما فوق -
to stay indoors and not move much.
بالبقاء في بيوتهم والتّقليل من الحركة.
How did this come about?
كيف وصلنا إلى هنا؟
It came from the way in which
السّبب وراء ذلك
Beijing has grown as a city.
هي الطّريقة الّتي نمت بها بكين كمدينة.
It's doubled over those 25 years, more than doubled,
لقد زاد سكّانها مرّتين أو أكثر في 25 عاما
from 10 million to 20 million.
من 10 إلى 20 مليون.
It's become a sprawling urban area
لقد صارت مدينة عملاقة وممتدّة
dependent on dirty fuel, dirty energy,
معتمدة على الوقود الملوّث، على الطّاقة الملوّثة،
particularly coal.
وبالخصوص الفحم.
China burns half the world's coal each year,
الصّين تحرق نصف الفحم العالميّ كلّ عام،
and that's why, it is a key reason why,
وهذا السّبب الرئيسيّ
it is the world's largest emitter
وراء كون الصّين أكبر باعث
of greenhouse gases.
للغازات المسببة للاحتباس الحراري.
At the same time, we have to recognize
في الوقت نفسه علينا الإقرار
that in that period China has grown remarkably.
بأنّ الصّين نمت بشكل رائع في نفس المدّة.
It has become the world's second largest economy.
هي الآن ثاني أكبر اقتصاد عالميّ.
Hundreds of millions of people
مئات الملايين من النّاس
have been lifted out of poverty.
أخرجوا من الفقر.
That's really important.
وهذا مهمّ للغاية.
But at the same time, the people of China
لكن في الوقت نفسه،
are asking the question:
يطرح الصّينيّون السّؤال التّالي:
What's the value of this growth
ما قيمة ذلك
if our cities are unlivable?
إذا صارت مدننا غير قابلة للعيش؟
They've analyzed, diagnosed
لقد حلّلوا وشخّصوا،
that this is an unsustainable path of growth
أنّ هذا طريق غير مستديم للنّموّ
and development.
وللتّطوّر.
China's planning to scale back coal.
تسعى الصين الآن إلى الحدّ من الفحم،
It's looking to build its cities in different ways.
وإلى بناء مدنها بشكل بديل.
Now, the growth of China
الآن، نموّ الصّين
is part of a dramatic change, fundamental change,
جزء من تغيير جذريّ
in the structure of the world economy.
في هيكل الاقتصاد العالميّ.
Just 25 years ago, the developing countries,
قبل 25 سنة، كانت البلدان النّامية،
the poorer countries of the world,
وهي أفقر البلدان،
were, notwithstanding being the vast majority of the people,
وأكثرها سكّانا،
they accounted for only about a third
لا تمثّل سوى
of the world's output.
ثلث الاقتصاد العالميّ.
Now it's more than half;
الآن هي تمثّل أكثر من نصفه،
25 years from now, it will probably be two thirds
وفي غضون 25 سنة، ربّما ثلثيه،
from the countries that we saw 25 years ago
بالنّسبة لبلدان معتبرة نامية
as developing.
25 سنة إلى الوراء،
That's a remarkable change.
هذه قفزة هائلة.
It means that most countries around the world,
هذا يعني أنّ أغلب بلدان العالم
rich or poor, are going to be facing
إن كانت فقيرة أم غنيّة، ستواجه
the two fundamental transformations
تحوّلين جذريّين
that I want to talk about and highlight.
أريد إبرازهما.
Now, the first of these transformations
أوّل هذه التّحوّلات
is the basic structural change
هو التّحوّل الهيكليّ
of the economies and societies
للاقتصاد والمجتمع
that I've already begun to illustrate
وهو ما بدأت أوضّحه
through the description of Beijing.
عبر وصفي لبيكين.
Fifty percent now in urban areas.
50 بالمائة من السّكّان في المدن.
That's going to go to 70 percent in 2050.
سيصيرون 70 بالمائة في 2050.
Over the next two decades, we'll see
طوال العقدين القادمين،
the demand for energy rise by 40 percent,
سوف نرى الطلب على الطاقة يكبر بنسبة 40 بالمائة،
and the growth in the economy and in the population
وتنامي الاقتصاد والسّكّان
is putting increasing pressure on our land,
سوف يضغط بشكل أكبر على الأرض،
on our water and on our forests.
والمياه والغابات.
This is profound structural change.
إذا عالجنا هذا التغيير الهيكليّ العميق
If we manage it in a negligent
بإهمال،
or a shortsighted way,
وقصر نظر،
we will create waste, pollution, congestion,
سنخلق النفايات والتلوّث والاكتظاظ،
destruction of land and forests.
وسنهدم أراضينا وغاباتنا.
If we think of those three areas that I have illustrated
إن فكّرنا في الميادين الثلاثة كما وصفتها
with my numbers — cities, energy, land —
بالأرقام ـ المدن والطاقة والأراضي ـ
if we manage all that badly,
إذا استغللناها بصفة سيّئة،
then the outlook for the lives and livelihoods
فمستقبل حياة ومعاش
of the people around the world
سكّان الأرض
would be poor and damaged.
سيكون فقيرا ومتضرّرا.
And more than that,
وزيادة عن ذلك،
the emissions of greenhouse gases would rise,
ستزيد الغازات المسببة للاحتباس الحراري،
with immense risks to our climate.
بكلّ ما تمثّله من أخطار على المناخ.
Concentrations of greenhouse gases
تركيز الغازات المسببة للاحتباس الحراري
in the atmosphere are already
في الجوّ
higher than they've been for millions of years.
بلغ حاليّا أعلى معدّل منذ ملايين السّنين،
If we go on increasing those concentrations,
إذا ما تمادينا في زيادة هذه المعدّلات،
we risk temperatures over the next century or so
فسوف نواجه خطر درجات حرارة
that we have not seen on this planet
لم نشهدها على كوكبنا
for tens of millions of years.
منذ عشرات ملايين السّنين.
We've been around as Homo sapiens —
تواجدنا كهومو سابين
that's a rather generous definition, sapiens —
ـ وهي عبارة كريمة أكثر مما ينبغي ـ
for perhaps a quarter of a million years, a quarter of a million.
لحوالي ربع مليون سنة.
We risk temperatures we haven't seen
وفي ظرف عقد صرنا نواجه خطر درجات حرارة
for tens of millions of years over a century.
لم نشهدها منذ عشرات ملايين السّنين.
That would transform the relationship
هذا قد يغير العلاقة
between human beings and the planet.
بين الانسان وكوكبنا الأرض.
It would lead to changing deserts,
قد يغير الصحاري،
changing rivers, changing patterns of hurricanes,
والوديان وشكل الأعاصير
changing sea levels,
ومستوى مياه البحر،
hundreds of millions of people,
مئات ملايين الناس،
perhaps billions of people who would have to move,
ربما مليارات الناس قد تضطر للرحيل،
and if we've learned anything from history,
وإذا تعلمنا من دروس الماضي،
that means severe and extended conflict.
فهذا يعني حروبًا مستعصية ومنتشرة.
And we couldn't just turn it off.
ولن يكون بمقدورنا تفادي ذلك.
You can't make a peace treaty with the planet.
لا يمكن إجراء معاهدة سلام مع الأرض،
You can't negotiate with the laws of physics.
ولا مناقشة قوانين الفيزياء.
You're in there. You're stuck.
نحن هنا، في مأزق.
Those are the stakes we're playing for,
هذه الرهانات التي بين أيدينا،
and that's why we have to make this second transformation,
ولهذا علينا القيام بالتحول الثاني،
the climate transformation,
التحول المناخي،
and move to a low-carbon economy.
والانتقال إلى اقتصاد منخفض الكربون.
Now, the first of these transformations
أما التحول الأول،
is going to happen anyway.
فهو قادم لا محالة.
We have to decide whether to do it well or badly,
وعلينا أن نقرر النجاح أو الإخفاق
the economic, or structural, transformation.
في هذا التحول الاقتصادي والهيكلي.
But the second of the transformations,
لكن التحول الثاني،
the climate transformations, we have to decide to do.
التحول المناخي، فعلينا أن نقرر ما سنقوم به.
Those two transformations face us
هذان التحولان يوجهاننا
in the next two decades.
في العقدين القادمين.
The next two decades are decisive
العقدان القادمان مصيريان
for what we have to do.
لما علينا القيام به.
Now, the more I've thought about this,
كلما فكرت مزيدًا،
the two transformations coming together,
في التحولين القادمين،
the more I've come to realize
كلما اقتنعت
that this is an enormous opportunity.
أنها فرصة كبيرة.
It's an opportunity which we can use
يمكننا ربحها
or it's an opportunity which we can lose.
أو خسارتها.
And let me explain through those three key areas
فلأفسر لكم الميادين الأساسية الثلاثة
that I've identified: cities, energy and land.
التي حددتها: المدن والطاقة والأراضي.
And let me start with cities.
ولأبدأ بالمدن.
I've already described the problems of Beijing:
وصفت سابقًا مشاكل بكين:
pollution, congestion, waste and so on.
تلوث واكتظاظ ونفايات...
Surely we recognize that in many of our cities
وهو ما نلاحظه في الكثير من مدننا
around the world.
حول العالم.
Now, with cities, like life but particularly cities,
في تخطيط مدننا، كما في حياتنا،
you have to think ahead.
علينا التفكير بشكل مسبق.
The cities that are going to be built —
المدن التي ستبنى
and there are many, and many big ones —
- وهي كثيرة، وأغلبها كبيرة-
we have to think of how to design them
علينا أن نفكر في تخطيطها
in a compact way
بشكل متلاحم
so we can save travel time and we can save energy.
لنقلل من مدة السفر واستهلاك الطاقة.
The cities that already are there, well established,
المدن التي بنيت سابقًا،
we have to think about renewal and investment in them
علينا أن نفكر في تجديدها والاستثمار فيها
so that we can connect ourselves much better
كي نربطها ببعضها البعض بشكل أفضل،
within those cities, and make it easier,
وكي نسهل
encourage more people, to live closer to the center.
ونشجع الناس أن يسكنوا أقرب إلى المركز.
We've got examples building around the world
ولدينا أمثلة كثيرة حول العالم
of the kinds of ways in which we can do that.
لتحقيق ذلك.
The bus rapid transport system in Bogotá in Colombia
نظام الحافلات السريعة في بوغوتا بكولمبيا
is a very important case of how to move around
مثال ممتاز
safely and quickly in a non-polluting way
للتنقل بأمان وسرعة ودون تلوث:
in a city: very frequent buses,
حافلات كثيرة
strongly protected routes, the same service, really,
في طرقات مخصصة لها ومحمية، نفس الخدمة حقًا،
as an underground railway system,
كالمترو تحت الأرض،
but much, much cheaper
لكن أرخص بكثير
and can be done much more quickly,
وسهلة الإنشاء،
a brilliant idea in many more cities
فكرة متألقة
around the world that's developing.
يتم تطبيقها في مدن كثيرة أخرى حول العالم.
Now, some things in cities do take time.
بعض المشاريع تستلزم وقتًا طويلًا،
Some things in cities can happen much more quickly.
وأخرى يمكن تطبيقها بشكل أسرع.
Take my hometown, London.
في مدينتي الأصلية، لندن، في 1952،
In 1952, smog in London killed 4,000 people
قتل الدخان 4000 ساكن
and badly damaged the lives of many, many more.
وأثر سلبًا على حياة عدد أكثر من السكان
And it happened all the time.
وكانت ظاهرة متكررة.
For those of you live outside London in the U.K.
البريطانيون من بينكم ممن يعيشون خارج لندن
will remember it used to be called The Smoke.
يتذكرون اسم لندن القديم: الدخان.
That's the way London was.
هكذا كانت لندن،
By regulating coal, within a few years
وبتنظيم استعمال الفحم،
the problems of smog were rapidly reduced.
في ضرف سنين تقلصت مشكلة الدخان.
I remember the smogs well.
أتذكر الدخان جيدًا.
When the visibility dropped to [less] than
حين كانت الرؤية لا تتجاوز
a few meters,
بضع أمتار،
they stopped the buses and I had to walk.
كانت الحافلات تتوقف.
This was the 1950s.
كان ذلك في الخمسينات.
I had to walk home three miles from school.
وكان علي المشي ثلاثة أميال من المدرسة للمنزل.
Again, breathing was a hazardous activity.
كان التنفس خطيرًا.
But it was changed. It was changed by a decision.
لكن كل ذلك تغير بفعل قرار.
Good decisions can bring good results,
القرارات الجيدة تدلي بنتائجها،
striking results, quickly.
نتائج مدهشة وسريعة،
We've seen more: In London, we've introduced the congestion charge,
ثم رأينا المزيد: في لندن خلقت ضريبة الاكتظاظ،
actually quite quickly and effectively,
بسرعة ونجاعة،
and we've seen great improvements
وشهدنا تحسنات جبارة
in the bus system, and cleaned up the bus system.
في نظام الحافلات،
You can see that the two transformations I've described,
يمكنكم ملاحظة أن التحولين الذين وصفتهما،
the structural and the climate,
الهيكلي والمناخي،
come very much together.
دائما مرتبطان.
But we have to invest. We have to invest in our cities,
لكن علينا الاستثمار، علينا الاستثمار في مدننا،
and we have to invest wisely, and if we do,
وبشكل حكيم، وإذا قمنا بذلك،
we'll see cleaner cities, quieter cities, safer cities,
فسنرى مدنًا أكثر نظافة وهدوء وأمانًا،
more attractive cities, more productive cities,
مدنًا أجمل وأكثر إنتاجية،
and stronger community in those cities —
ومجتمعات أقوى في هذه المدن،
public transport, recycling, reusing,
النقل العام وإعادة التدوير والاستعمال،
all sorts of things that bring communities together.
هي الأشياء التي توحد المجتمعات.
We can do that, but we have to think,
كل هذا بمقدورنا، لكن علينا أن نفكر،
we have to invest, we have to plan.
ونستثمر ونخطط.
Let me turn to energy.
فلأنتقل الآن إلى مضوع الطاقة.
Now, energy over the last 25 years
استعمال الطاقة في 25 سنة الماضية
has increased by about 50 percent.
ازداد ب 50 بالمئة.
Eighty percent of that comes from fossil fuels.
80 بالمئة من المحروقات.
Over the next 20 years,
طوال 25 سنة القادمة،
perhaps it will increase by another 40 percent or so.
ربما سيزداد بحوالي 40 بالمئة.
We have to invest strongly in energy,
علينا أن نستثمر في الطاقة،
we have to use it much more efficiently,
وأن نستعملها بحكمة،
and we have to make it clean.
وأن نجعلها نظيفة.
We can see how to do that.
فلنفكر كيف نقوم بهذا.
Take the example of California.
ولنأخذ مثال كاليفورنيا.
It would be in the top 10 countries in the world
كاليفورنيا بإمكانها أن تكون من أقوى 10 بلدا في العالم
if it was independent.
لو كانت مستقلة،
I don't want to start any —
أنا لا أقصد بدأ أي ...
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
California's a big place.
كاليفورنيا مكان شاسع.
In the next five or six years,
في الأعوام الخمسة أو الستة القادمة،
they will likely move from
ستنتقل كاليفورنيا على الأرجح
around 20 percent in renewables —
من 20 بالمئة من الطاقات المتجددة
wind, solar and so on —
- كالريح والشمس وغيرها -
to over 33 percent,
إلى أكثر من 33 بالمئة،
and that would bring California back
ما سيعيد كاليفورنيا
to greenhouse gas emissions in 2020
في 2020 إلى معدل الغازات المسببة للاحتباس الحراري
to where they were in 1990,
لم كانت عليه عام 1990،
a period when the economy in California
رغم أن اقتصادها تضاعف
would more or less have doubled.
في نفس هذه المدة.
That's a striking achievement.
هذا إنجاز باهر،
It shows what can be done.
يرينا ما بإمكاننا فعله،
Not just California — the incoming government of India
وبخلاف كاليفورنيا فالهند أيضًا
is planning to get solar technology
تبرمج لاستعمال التكنولوجيا الشمسية
to light up the homes
للإنارة المنزلية
of 400 million people
لأكثر من 400 مليون شخص
who don't have electricity in India.
مفتقرين للكهرباء.
They've set themselves a target of five years.
هدفهم القيام بذلك في 5 سنوات.
I think they've got a good chance of doing that.
أظن أنهم سينجحون.
We'll see, but what you're seeing now
سنرى، ولكن ما نشاهده الأن
is people moving much more quickly.
هو شعب يتحرك بسرعة أكبر،
Four hundred million, more than the population
400 مليون شخص
of the United States.
أكثر من كل الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية.
Those are the kinds of ambitions now
هذه طموحات الناس
people are setting themselves
الآن
in terms of rapidity of change.
على مستوى سرعة التحولات.
Again, you can see
مرة أخرى
good decisions can bring quick results,
ترون قرارات جيدة تأتي بنتائج سريعة،
and those two transformations, the economy and the structure
وهذان التحولان، الاقتصاد والهيكلة من جهة،
and the climate and the low carbon,
والمناخ وتخفيض الكربون من جهة أخرى،
are intimately intertwined.
مرتبطان بصفة وثيقة.
Do the first one well, the structural,
قم بالتحول الأول، الهيكلي، بنجاح
the second one on the climate
سيأتي الثاني، المناخي
becomes much easier.
بسهولة أكبر.
Look at land,
أنظر للأرض،
land and particularly forests.
الأرض وخاصةً الغابات.
Forests are the hosts to valuable
الغابات تأوي
plant and animal species.
فصائل نباتية وحيوانية ثمينة.
They hold water in the soil
الغابات تخزن الماء في ترابها
and they take carbon dioxide out of the atmosphere,
وتنظف الهواء من ثاني أكسيد الكربون،
fundamental to the tackling of climate change.
مهمة أساسية في التصدي للتغير المناخي.
But we're losing our forests.
لكننا بصدد خسارة غاباتنا.
In the last decade, we've lost a forest area
في العقد الماضي، خسرنا مساحة غابية
the size of Portugal,
بما يعادل مساحة البرتغال،
and much more has been degraded.
ومساحات غابية أكبر تدهورت.
But we're already seeing
لكننا واعون
that we can do so much about that.
بما يمكن القيام به.
We can recognize the problem, but we can also
نقدر أن نعترف بالمشكل،
understand how to tackle it.
لكن نقدر أيضًا أن نفهم كيف نعالجه.
In Brazil, the rate of deforestation
في البرازيل، معدل إزالة الغابات
has been reduced by 70 percent
تقلص 70 بالمائة
over the last 10 years.
في العقد الماضي.
How? By involving local communities,
كيف؟ بتدخل السكان المحليين،
investing in their agriculture and their economies,
باستثمارهم في فلاحتهم واقتصادهم،
by monitoring more carefully,
بمراقبة أكثر حذرًا،
by enforcing the law more strictly.
وبتنفيذ القانون بأكثر صرامة.
And it's not just stopping deforestation.
وهذا لا يوقف فقط إزالة الغابات،
That's of course of first and fundamental importance,
الذي هو بالطبع الهدف الأول والأساسي،
but it's also regrading degraded land,
بل هذا يجدد الغابات المتدهورة،
regenerating, rehabilitating degraded land.
ويعيد تأهيلها.
I first went to Ethiopia in 1967.
ذهبت إلى إثيوبيا أول مرة في 1967.
It was desperately poor. In the following years,
كانت فقيرة بشكل فظيع.
it suffered devastating famines
وفي الأعوام التالية، عانت من مجاعات
and profoundly destructive social conflict.
وصراعات اجتماعية مدمرة.
Over the last few years, actually more than a few,
خلال الأعوام الكثيرة الماضية،
Ethiopia has been growing much more rapidly.
نمت أثيوبيا بسرعة متزايدة.
It has ambitions to be a middle-income country
هي تطمح أن تصير ضمن البلدان متوسطة الدخل
15 years from now
في ظرف 15 سنة
and to be carbon neutral.
وأن تصير غير مسهمة في الكربون.
Again, I think it's a strong ambition
مرة أخرى، هذه طموحات كبيرة،
but it is a plausible one.
لكن ممكنة.
You're seeing that commitment there.
ترون هنا الالتزام.
You're seeing what can be done.
ترون ما يمكن فعله.
Ethiopia is investing in clean energy.
أثيوبيا تستثمر في الطاقة النظيفة.
It's working in the rehabilitation of land.
وتعمل على إعادة تأهيل اراضيها.
In Humbo, in southwest Ethiopia,
في هومبو، جنوب غرب أثيوبيا،
a wonderful project
مشروع باهر
to plant trees on degraded land
لزراعة أشجار في الأراضي المتدهورة
and work with local communities
وللعمل مع السكان المحليين
on sustainable forest management
على إدارة مستديمة للغابات
has led to big increases in living standards.
أدى إلى زيادة كبيرة في مستوى العيش.
So we can see, from Beijing to London,
بإمكاننا أن نرى من بكين إلى لندن،
from California to India,
من كاليفورنيا إلى الهند،
from Brazil to Ethiopia,
من البرازيل إلى إثيوبيا،
we do understand
وأن نفهم
how to manage those two transformations,
كيف نعالج هذين التحولين،
the structural and the climate.
الهيكلي والمناخي.
We do understand how to manage those well.
نفهم كيف نديرهما بطريقة صحيحة.
And technology is changing very rapidly.
والتكنولوجيا تتطور بسرعة.
I don't have to list all those things
لن أعدد كل هذه الأشياء
to an audience like this,
لمستمعين مثلكم،
but you can see the electric cars,
لكن بإمكانكم رؤية السيارات الكهربائية،
you can see the batteries using new materials.
والبطاريات التي تستعمل مواد جديدة.
You can see that we can manage remotely now
بإمكانكم رؤية التحكم عن بعد
our household appliances on our mobile phones when we're away.
في منازلنا عن طريق التطبيقات في هاتفنا.
You can see better insulation.
بإمكانكم رؤية العزل الحراري الأنجع.
And there's much more coming.
والكثير لا يزال في الطريق.
But, and it's a big but,
لكن، وهي نقطة هامة،
the world as a whole
العالم كمجموعة
is moving far too slowly.
يتحرك ببطء.
We're not cutting emissions in the way we should.
لسنا نحد من انبعاثات الغازات بالشكل الكافي.
We're not managing those structural transformations
لسنا ندير هذه التحولات الهيكلية
as we can.
على أحسن ما نستطيع.
The depth of understanding of the immense risks of climate change
لم نصل بعد إلى فهم عميق
are not there yet.
لخطر التغيرات المناخية.
of the attractiveness of what we can do
لمدى جاذبية
is not there yet.
ما يمكننا فعله.
We need political pressure to build.
نحتاج إلى ضغط سياسي لنتقدم.
We need leaders to step up.
نحتاج إلى قادة ليدخلوا الميدان.
We can have better growth,
باستطاعتنا أن نحقق نموًا أحسن،
better climate, a better world.
مناخًا أحسن، عالمًا أحسن،
We can make,
باستطاعتنا،
by managing those two transformations well,
إذا عالجنا هذين التحولين بشكل صحيح،
the next 100 years the best of centuries.
أن نجعل القرن القادم أجمل القرون.
If we make a mess of it,
إذا أخفقنا،
we, you and me, if we make a mess of it,
نحن، أنتم وأنا،
if we don't manage those transformations properly,
في معالجة هذين التحولين بشكل سليم،
it will be, the next 100 years
سيكون القرن القادم،
will be the worst of centuries.
أسوء القرون.
That's the major conclusion
هذه هي الخلاصة الأساسية
of the report on the economy and climate
للتقرير حول الاقتصاد والمناخ
chaired by ex-President Felipe Calderón of Mexico,
الذي قام به الرئيس المكسيكي السابق فليب كالديرون،
and I co-chaired that with him,
بمشاركتي،
and we handed that report yesterday
وقدمنا هذا التقرير البارحة
here in New York, in the United Nations Building
هنا في نيويورك، في مقر الأمم المتحدة
to the Secretary-General of the U.N.,
إلى الأمين العام للأمم المتحدة،
Ban Ki-moon.
بان كي مون.
We know that we can do this.
نعرف أن كل هذا ممكن.
Now, two weeks ago,
أخيرًا، منذ أسبوعين،
I became a grandfather for the fourth time.
صرت جدًا للمرة الرابعة.
Our daughter —
ابنتنا -
(Baby cries) (Laughter) (Applause) —
(رضيع يبكي) (ضحك) (تصفيق)
Our daughter gave birth to Rosa here in New York
ابنتنا أنجبت روزا هنا في نيويورك
two weeks ago. Here are Helen and Rosa.
منذ أسبوعين، ها هي هلن وها هي روزا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Two weeks old.
عمرها أسبوعان.
Are we going to look our grandchildren in the eye
هل سننظر في عيون أحفادنا
and tell them that we understood the issues,
ونقول لهم أننا فهمنا الرهانات،
that we recognized the dangers and the opportunities,
وفهمنا الأخطار والفرص،
and still we failed to act?
ورغم ذلك لم نقم بشيء؟
Surely not. Let's make the next 100 years
حتمًا لا. فلنجعل القرن القادم
the best of centuries.
أحسن القرون.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)